בוקר טוב, Boker tov, welcome to our new מסכת, masechet, כריתות. Keritot.
A few introductory remarks before we begin. It's another short מסכת, masechet,
it's about 30 דף. daf. It's like all these ones at the
end are about a month long.
It is in many ways more similar to a normal מסכת masechet
you would have in non-קדשים, Kodashim, in the fact that if you
think about the general topics we've been covering in קדשים, Kodashim, let's
put חולין Chullin aside, it's been either how you bring קרבנות korbanot
and the מצוות mitzvot specific to the exact process of bringing קרבנות,
korbanot, or it's more about sort of metaphysical states, things like their
קדושה kedusha and the implications of their קדושה kedusha and transferring their
קדושה kedusha and so on. כריתות Keritot is more similar to your
standard מסכת masechet that it's really about מצוות. mitzvot. It's much more
about sort of questions about obligations and transgressions.
And so the emphasis about it are when do you bring a
קרבן חטאת? korban chatat? And you bring a קרבן חטאת korban chatat
for the sins for which you're חייב כרת. chayav karet. So first
there's a discussion about which are the sins that you are חייב
כרת chayav karet for. Then there's the question about, well, it's not
all about חטאת, chatat, it's about the things that are similar to
a חטאת. chatat. There's an אשם תלוי, asham talui, which is what
you bring when you're not sure that you've done a sin that
you would otherwise bring a חטאת. chatat. There are other types of
אשמות, ashamot, which are sin offerings but they're not חטאות. chatatot. There
are חטאות chatatot that are not about sin. There are חטאות chatatot
that are about מחוסרי כפרה, mechusrei kappara, about like a יולדת, yoledet,
a woman who gives childbirth brings a חטאת, chatat, and that really
isn't about sin. If you remember we discussed a while ago about
חטאת chatat also has the sense of really of cleansing, not so
much about sin, and it's about making, bringing somebody, finishing a state
of טומאה. tumah. So part of the מסכת masechet deals with the
different types of obligations that all of the different things that are
in the broadly speaking חטאת chatat category. The other thing it discusses
is the question about how many חטאות chatatot would you bring? The
idea that if you did multiple sins in one state of forgetfulness,
because you only bring a חטאת, chatat, a sin offering, if you
are שוגג. shogeg. But let's say you did the same sin multiple
times, or you did multiple different sins but they were roughly in
the same category. Do you bring one חטאת chatat or do you
bring multiple חטאות? chatatot? If you forgot it's שבת Shabbat and you
do multiple מלאכות, melachot, how many חטאות chatatot do you bring? So
all of these questions, as you could see, speak much more to
the question about obligations,
מצוות, mitzvot, עבירות, aveirot, and so on, and not the questions about
how the process of bringing a קרבן korban or the issue about,
as I said, about like the metaphysics of the קדושה. kedusha. So
in that way it is a מסכת masechet that is much, much
feels much more like a traditional מסכת. masechet. That being said, let's
see, except that it's about a קדשים Kodashim theme. That being said,
it is one of the five מסכתות masechtot that the language
has more of a ירושלמי Yerushalmi feel. It's not the classic Babylonian
Aramaic. If you remember we had a discussion about that before, where
it, the general scholarly consensus is that that probably means that it
was redacted earlier or certainly redacted in a different location in בבל,
Bavel, סורא, Sura, פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, the different sources, thank you, and the
one that actually was a location in which it was the Aramaic
was closer to the Palestinian Aramaic, to the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
Aramaic. So that's on, that being said, the text is not as
problematic as the text in תמורה. Temurah. If you were noticing, I
mean
in
תמורה, Temurah, there were so many parentheses and brackets and different variants
on the side. Here, while the language, it's a different, it reflects
a different redacting, nevertheless the actual text itself seems much
less problematic. There seems to be, in terms of the stability of
the text, and that probably has to do with the fact that
it was probably learned a lot more for the reasons I said,
that in other ways it's much more similar to a traditional מסכת.
masechet. Now, so that's in terms of what to expect from the
מסכת masechet itself. I will also say in terms of the מפרשים,
mefarshim, you will notice for example on this first page and on
עמוד א amud aleph and the עמוד ב, amud bet, there is
no תוספות Tosafot and there is a huge amount of רש״י. Rashi.
Now, there is תוספות Tosafot in this מסכת, masechet, but it is
extremely sparse. And therefore the pages would be huge in terms of
the amount of גמרא. Gemara. But to counterbalance that we have a
lot of רש״י, Rashi, which keeps the pages of the size of
the page down, which is good for us, our ability to accomplish
it. Like if anybody knows what a דף daf in ברכות Berachot
looks like and how much text there is on one page, so
it's a good thing there's a lot of רש״י Rashi to counterpart
the lack of תוספות. Tosafot. But the point is that the רש״י
Rashi here is way overly verbose. So for example, our first משנה
mishna lists the 36 types of sins that you get כרת karet
for. This רש״י Rashi goes and details every single sin, what's the
פסוק pasuk that says don't do it, what's the פסוק pasuk that
proves that it's כרת, karet, extremely, extremely verbose, which of course gets
you curious and says, is this really רש״י? Rashi? And רש״י Rashi
knows how to be a lot more terse. So believe it or
not, there is, although I looked in my standard reference book which
is Strack and Stemberger on the תלמוד *Talmud*, they mentioned a few
מסכתות *Masechtos* where it's probably not רש״י *Rashi*. They did not mention
this, but the Jewish Encyclopedia under the heading of רש״י *Rashi*, right,
that was what we had before, we had the Encyclopedia Judaica and
now the Jewish Encyclopedia is free and available on the web. The
Jewish Encyclopedia under רש״י *Rashi* says yes, that scholars have basically already
come to the conclusion that the רש״י *Rashi* printed on כריתות *Keritot*
is not רש״י *Rashi*. Zunz was the first one
who demonstrated that this is not רש״י *Rashi*. So, but thankfully because
it's so big and I have to read רש״י *Rashi* when I'm
preparing, but you don't have to read it when we're doing the
דף *Daf* to keep the size of the דף *Daf* down to
a reasonable size. I don't know what it is. Probably one of
his תלמידים *Talmidim* or something like that. I'm not sure we know
who it is. Okay, so that is in way of introduction. Let's
get started with our new מסכת Masechet. *Masechet*.
So, שלשים ושש כריתות בתורה Shloshim Veshesh Karetot Batorah. *Shloshim v'shesh kritot
b'Torah*. There are 36 examples of כרת Karet *Kares* in the תורה
Torah, *Torah*. And the reason we're mentioning it, why do we care
about כרת karet *Kares* in a מסכת masechet *Masechet* about קדשים *Kodshim*?
Is because things that you get כרת karet, *Kares* for, if you
do them במזיד *b'meizid*, right, willfully, intentionally, are things that if you
do it בשוגג *b'shogeg*, unintentionally, you would bring a קרבן חטאת Korban
Chatat, *Korban Chatat*. Okay, so therefore it is relevant because it is
the basis for which sins you would bring a קרבן חטאת korban
chatas? *Korban Chatat* if you do it בשוגג *b'shogeg*. כרת karet. *Kares*
is the sin that you get, as a punishment you get for
doing a sin במזיד *b'meizid*. Now, that does not mean there cannot
be more severe punishments. A number of these things, if there was
warning, you would get התראה *hatrah* and witnesses, you would get put
to death. חילול שבת chilul Shabbos *Chilul Shabbos* is מות יומת *mos
yumas*. But if there's no witnesses or there's no warning, then God
will take care of it. If it's an intentional sin, it is
כרת karet *Kares*. Other types of things are only כרת karet *Kares*,
right? יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* is only כרת karet. *Kares*.
Eating, eating חמץ Chametz. בפסח *chametz b'Pesach*, well that's a לאו lav,
*lav* and then there's a question that if you can, you get
מלקות *malkus* instead of כרת karet. *Kares*. But if there's witnesses and
warning, there's always a possibility that you would get lashes or depending
on the sin, or that you would get put to death depending
on the sin. Or some sins only have כרת karet, *Kares* as
the consequence, not lashes and not מיתה mita *misa*. But most classically,
well, things like עריות Arayot. *ervos*, most classically though, you would, if
there would be lashes or מיתה mita. *misa*, but if there are
no witnesses and no warning, then it's between you and God and
then it is כרת karet? *Kares*. There's even in the case where
you would get lashes, there's a question about whether you would give
him lashes and exempt the person from כרת Kareth. *Kares* and we
will see from that it's lashes instead of כרת Kareth *Kares* or
not. We'll see about that. Now, what is כרת Kareth. *Kares*?
The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* most oftenly when it talks about כרת Kareth
*Kares*, right, the soul will be excised ונכרתה הנפש ההיא venichrat hanefesh
hahi. מעמיה *v'nichresa hanefesh hahi me'ameha*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* most oftenly
when it refers to it refers to a foreshortened life. In particular,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that somebody who dies between the ages
of 50 and 60 is considered a מיתה mita של כרת Kareth.
*misa shel kares*. So that's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s understanding, a foreshortened
life. רש״י *Rashi* in a number of places identifies כרת Kareth *Kares*
with the concept of ערירי *ariri*, childless. And רש״י *Rashi* says that
it means that the person will not have children. Sometimes he says
both, a foreshortened life and you won't have children. Anyway, that's רש״י
*Rashi* sometimes adds or replaces it with the concept of childlessness, which
again, these ideas are very harsh when you try to make the
reverse inference. Like if somebody died before the age of 60, do
we assume they died from כרת Kareth *Kares*? If somebody doesn't have
kids, I mean is that how we interpret it? Obviously, just because
A leads to B doesn't mean that B implies A, right? That's
just simple logic. But nevertheless, that's obviously something to be extremely sensitive
to, you don't even want to be implying versus suggesting that.
Wasn't there this אמורא *Amora* who made a big party once he
reached the, I
understand, but that just means you're definitely not in that category. It
doesn't mean that, right, if P then Q does not mean if
Q then P. Okay, and that's I think something to be very
sensitive to, extremely sensitive to. I mean obviously dying an early death
nowadays, under 60 is considered to be very young and childlessness, I
mean these are real tragedies, you don't have to exacerbate it by
thinking that that's the idea of כרת Kareth *Kares*. Now, the other
thing to mention though is the רמב״ם *Rambam*. The רמב״ם *Rambam* sort
of frames a lot of these things like the whole question about
what's עולם הבא Olam Haba *Olam Ha-ba*. In the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
עולם הבא Olam Haba, *Olam Ha-ba* is much more about what happens
in this world after משיח *Mashiach* comes. For the רמב״ם *Rambam*, עולם
הבא Haba. *Olam Ha-ba* is what happens to your soul after the
body dies. It's the world of the souls. So similarly, although the
first explanations of כרת Kareth. *Kares* I gave you were about a
type of a this-worldly punishment, the רמב״ם *Rambam* emphasizes that כרת Kareth
*Kares* means that your soul is cut off from עולם הבא *Olam
Ha-ba* when you die. Exactly, and so that is, that's the רמב״ם
*Rambam* and that's the general approach the רמב״ם *Rambam* has about these
types of issues in general. Okay, so 36 כריתות בתורה *kritot b'Torah*.
Well, yes.
The question also is, is that like absolute? I mean is there
a way, that after your soul somehow suffers? I mean again, the
רמב״ם *Rambam* didn't really
buy... I mean considered to be a metaphor more the idea of
the גמרא Gemara. that your soul is punished in גיהנום Gehennam and
so on because the רמב"ם Rambam understood the fate of your soul
after death was a more sort of natural state based on the
religious based on sort of the how the soul had developed in
this life. He did not sort of see עולם הבא as much
as a שכר ועונש Sachar Ve'onesh as much more of a sort
of natural metaphysical consequence. But anyway, we're not getting into that discussion
now. Yes.
According to רש"י, Rashi, a long life, so it means it's for
sure you're not...
presumably,
presumably, although who knows, you know, why צדיק ורע לו רשע וטוב
לו, Tzaddik Vera Lo Rasha Vetov Lo, who knows how God operates.
Okay, so let's take a look. שלשים ושש כריתות בתורה. So all
that before reading the first four after before four words of the
משנה, Mishnah, but okay, important introductory material. 36 times types of things
you can get כרת Karet, for in the תורה, Torah which as
we said will lead to a קרבן korban חטאת, chatat. which is
the focus of this מסכת. masechet. What are they? We're going to
start with the עריות. Arayot הבא על האם, Haba Al Ha'em, a
man has sex with his mother, ועל אשת האב, Ve'al Eshet Ha'av,
or his stepmother, his father's wife, even if it's not his mother,
ועל
הכלה, Ve'al Hakallah, or it doesn't mean a kallah, it means his
daughter-in-law, his son's wife. הבא על הזכר, Haba Al Hazachar,
now some of these are also of course also married women, so
as a question by these is, you know, do those statuses continue
to obtain after they are divorced or not? Anyway, we'll talk about
the right some statuses do, a forbidden עריות Arayot, do obtain even
after the relationship is severed, others do not. We'll talk about that
in the גמרא. Gemara.
Now, those so now we switch from heterosexual to non-heterosexual. No, we're
going to get back to other עריות, Arayot, but the reason we
sort of break now is because we're focusing on the first on
the ones that you're חייב מיתה Chayav Mitah for, and these first
three are not only you're חייב מיתה, Chayav Mitah, but that you
are even חייב בסקילה. Chayav Biskilah. Okay,
so one minute, okay,
right, one minute, yes, they're all סקילה. Skilah. Now, הבא על הזכר
ועל הבהמה, Haba Al Hazachar Ve'al Habehemah,
a man who has sex with another man
or bestiality, an act of bestiality. What?
Why do they do זכר Zachar instead of זכר? Zachar?
I'm not I don't know. It's a good question. I think actually
רש"י Rashi in סנהדרין Sanhedrin discusses it having to do with I
remember there's a רש"י Rashi in סנהדרין Sanhedrin about that, I'll have
to check. Okay.
Assuming that this is addressed to a man.
Oh, of course, thank you for pointing that out. We're always assuming
that the implied subject is a man. The תורה Torah actually itself
though does it in its עריות, Arayot right? The תורה Torah says
ואיש אשר ישכב את אשת אביו. Ve'ish Asher Yishkav Et Eshet Aviv.
It's not here a woman הבא.
I understand, but I'm saying well we're about to get to a
woman in a minute. ואשה המביאה הבהמה עליה, Ve'ishah Hamviah Habehemah Aleha,
right, a woman who brings the animal on her. I understand, but
I'm saying I'm saying that that but if you read through the
תורה's Torah. פרשת עריות Parshat Arayot in אחרי מות Acharei Mot and
קדושים, Kedoshim, also it doesn't say an aunt can't have sex with
her nephew. It says a man can't have sex with his, you
know, father's sister or his father's brother's sister. So the implied subject
is a I mean, yes, it's true, but it's reflecting exactly the
way it's framed in the תורה.
Torah Yes, the other part is also subject to the same.
Yes, that is correct, and the גמרא Gemara has to say how
do you know in all these עריות Arayot that the woman also
is חייבת מיתה, Chayevet Mitah, and it learns from a פסוק, Pasuk,
I mean one or two places the תורה Torah does say it,
like by by by adultery, but in general the גמרא Gemara learns
it out from the פסוק Pasuk about
ומתו גם שניהם, Umesu Gam Sheneihem, that, you know, a general principle
that the woman involved in these acts is considered to be the
same sin as the man. But yes, it is true that the
תורה Torah, describes it from the man's perspective and the משנה Mishnah
does the same. That is absolutely correct.
And your point applies to the first items also, הבא על האם.
Haba Al Ha'em.
Exactly. It's not הבא על בנו. Haba Al Beno. Right.
But this would exclude women, and a woman is permitted to הבא
על בנה. Haba Al Benah.
I understand. Right. It is all assuming the male subject. Correct.
Okay, except for the case of ואשה המביאה בהמה עליה Ve'ishah Hamviah
Behemah Aleha where there is no man to talk about. Okay. הבא
על אשה ובתה, Haba Al Ishah Uvitah, again, a man who has
sex with a woman and her daughter, which also would be true
about a woman and her mother because that would be a woman
and her daughter just, you know, reversed. ואשת איש, Ve'eshet Ish,
a married woman. All of those are are also חייב מיתה. Chayav
Mitah. So this entire first list is חייב מיתה, Chayav Mitah, but
we the first thing was סקילה, Skilah, then we moved to other
forms of the death penalty, but until now it's all חייב מיתה.
Chayav Mitah. Now we move on to עריות Arayot that is חייב
כרת Chayav Karet without actually being punishable by death by execution by
the court. הבא על אחותו, Haba Al Achoto, sex with a man
has sex with his sister, ועל אחות אביו, Ve'al Achot Aviv, his
father's sister, his aunt, ועל אחות אמו, Ve'al Achot Immo, his mother's
sister, also his aunt on his mother's side.
Now again, by the way, pointing out the whole issue about it
being male focused, it's not just how it's described, it's also that
also means that certain עריות arayot are forbidden and others are permitted.
A woman can have sex with her uncle, her father's brother or
her mother's brother. Actually the גמרא Gemara, speaks about how that that's
like an appropriate thing for an uncle to marry his niece. So
actually, so I mean there's, you know, discussions in the maybe we'll
get to it. What? Mordechai and Esther, according to the מדרש. Midrash.
Although no, actually, everybody assumed it was niece, but actually it was
his cousin. היא אסתר בת דודו. Hi Ester bat dodo. But it's
so funny that for some reason, probably because it's a conflating of...
there's also conflating of לקחה לו לבת. lakachlo l'bat. So you think
about he raised her, so you assume a different generation. But anyway,
but it is interesting about why conceptually is that different. A man
with his aunt or a woman with her uncle and so on.
Maybe we'll talk about that a little bit later. But you are
absolutely correct, it is not only described from the man's perspective, but
it also defines certain עריות arayot. as opposed to others. Okay, so
with an aunt, a man with his aunt, ועל אשת אחי אביו.
v'al eshet achi aviv.
Now his father's brother's wife. So his aunt that is even not,
you know, biologically related to him. Okay, his father's brother's wife. Now
in parentheses is ועל אשת אחי אמו, v'al eshet achi imo, his
mother's brother's wife. That is not there because as that is rabbinic,
that is not actually biblical. We'll talk about that later. Okay, but
that is why that is taken out. ועל, v'al, you can count
to make sure that it's still 36 even without that. ועל הנדה,
v'al haniddah, okay, a man who has sex with a woman who
is a נדה, niddah, that is חייב כרת, chayav karet, even if
it's his wife. והמגדף, v'hamigadef, now that's the end of the עריות.
arayot, A long list of עריות, arayot those that are חייב מיתה,
chayav mita, those that are חייב כרת. chayav karet. Notice that the
only ones that are כרת Karet that are not מיתה mita. are
basically נדה, niddah, sister, and aunt. Of course, sister I think is
the one that for us is sort of, you know, most problematic.
Like that's only כרת, Karet but a woman and her daughter is
מיתה. mita, You know, to us the whole idea of incest seems,
you know, much more deeply problematic than a man who has sex
with a woman, let's say, and her daughter. But... what? Might be.
I mean that's an interesting question.
All the עריות arayot addressed here?
Yeah, these are all the עריות arayot. that are dealt with.
So why is it that the
sister's...
alright, we'll talk about that, we have a whole גמרא Gemara to
look at on this whole mention.
Yeah, in ancient Egypt, the royal family always routinely did brother-sister marriage.
Interesting, interesting. Right. So could be that our sort of taboo abhorrence
of that is, you know, is more recent. You know, and let's
also not forget Freud, that, you know, taboos are for, you know,
you don't... taboos grow up about things that there's like a strong
יצר הרע yetzer hara for. Right? You don't have these taboos about
things that naturally people don't do.
So, you'll think about that one.
Anyway, so, alright. Now, so that's the end of the list of
עריות. והמגדף, v'hamigadef, a blasphemer.
There's a question exactly what מגדף migadef is, but we'll assume for
now that's what it means. ועובד עבודת כוכבים, v'oved avodat kochavim, an
idolater. Okay, these are things that are חייב מיתה, chayav mita, but
again if there's no witnesses and warning, then it is
כרת. Karet והנותן מזרעו למולך, v'hanoten mizar'o lamolech, if somebody passes over
from one of his children to the Molech worship. The question of
course is why is that not also עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? But
fine, we'll see about that, but that clearly is a case that
it is, you know, מיתה Mita, with warning and כרת Karet if
there is not witnesses and warning. ובעל
אוב, u'ba'al ov, somebody who does that type of necromancy known as
בעל אוב. ba'al ov.
ידעוני yidoni also, right?
Yeah, so we'll talk about all that in the גמרא. Gemara.
And now ובעל אוב, u'ba'al ov, where are we?
ומחלל שבת, v'mechallel Shabbat, there you go, obviously a case of חיוב
מיתה chiyuv mita if it's done with witnesses and warning, but כרת
Karet, without that.
What? You only get... you say if there are witnesses and warning?
Yes, from the top of the משנה. Mishnah.
No, some of these that even with witnesses and warning you do
not, like the case of sister or aunt. Okay, some of these
you do... there is no מיתה. mita But many of these there
is מיתה, but if there is no witnesses and warning, then it
is כרת. Karet
Yeah, but that's a whole question about do we say נפטר מידי
מיתתן, niftar midei mitatan,
we'll talk about that in the גמרא. Gemara, Okay, וטמא שאכל קודש,
v'tame she'achal kodesh,
if a person is טמא tame and eats קרבנות, korbanot, not if
the קרבן korban. is טמא, tame, that's a לאו, lav. but that
already to some degree desecrated or, you know, impinged on the קדושה
kedusha of the קרבן. korban But if the קרבן korban is not
טמא, tame, so it has its full קדושה kedusha and the person
is טמא, tame, that's a violating of the קדושה kedusha of the
קרבן Korban of the most weighty type, so that is a חייב
כרת. chayav karet. והבא אל המקדש טמא, v'haba el hamikdash tame,
if somebody is טמא tame and goes into the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, similar type of idea. These are things, by the way, that
there is no חיוב מיתה chiyuv mita at all. Okay, these are
just כרת. Karet Whether man or woman
also, right?
Yeah, of course. והאוכל, v'ha'ochel, now if you eat, what types of
forbidden food? And this is interesting because, you know, the things that
we have the greatest taboo around, let's say pork, is not כרת,
Karet, it's a simple לאו. lav. What are the things that are
כרת? Karet, חלב, chelev, fat, ודם, v'dam, the blood, ונותר ופיגול, v'notar
u'pigul,
and קרבנות korbanot that were left over or פיגול pigul that you
planned to... at the wrong time or the wrong place, whatever these
are things that are חייב כרת Chayav Kareth and again these are
clearly not מיתה, but these are כרת. kareis What?
Isn't one of those rabbinic פיגול Piggul like you know...
No, it is not rabbinic. It is whether it's it's not the
פיגול Piggul in תורה, Torah but its status is not rabbinic.
No, no, I mean I understand פיגול. Piggul. Wasn't פיגול Piggul in
תורה Torah, only if the wrong
time, not the wrong place? פיגול Piggul is only the wrong time,
but there also is by the wrong place. Wrong place is also...
yeah, it has it's not mentioned here explicitly. I will double check.
I am it's definitely not rabbinic and I am pretty positive that
it's also כרת kareis, and so on.
But but I'll double check that. I could be wrong. Okay, it's
been known to happen. Anyway,
now interestingly, okay, we're going to also see of course the one
other thing that is going to be that's going to come up
in a minute, which is also coming up for us, which is
the מאכלות אסורות Ma'achalot Assurot is פסח, Pesach, that the חמץ. Chametz
That's the other כרת. kareis. Now interestingly, why these things are כרת
more than other מאכלות אסורות? Ma'achalot Assurot? So what you will see
is the common denominator here is that they have a מקדש Mikdash
type of a resonance. Or you know, חלב Cheilev and דם Dam
are things that go on the מזבח Mizbeach
and therefore maybe also alternatively you could argue that they were eaten
maybe as a form of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. You get that
hint by
דם, Dam, לא תאכלו על הדם לא תנחשו ולא תעוננו, Lo To'chlu
Al HaDam Lo Tenachashu V'Lo Te'onenu, that it's said in פסוקים Psukim
relating to sort of witchcraft and עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. But also
there's a sense כי אני נתתיו לכם על המזבח לכפר. Ki Ani
Netativ Lachem Al HaMizbeach Lechaper. These are things that had they been
קרבנות Korbanot would be brought as sacrifices. And therefore for example there
is not a prohibition of the חלב Cheilev of a what do
you call it, of a חיה, Chaya, right? Because or an עוף,
Of, well there is no חלב Cheilev in עוף, Of, whatever, anyway
because those are things that would not have otherwise been sacrificed. So
that certainly seems to be why that these things around מקדש, Mikdash,
you know, have this greater weight and have this sense of כרת.
חמץ Chametz is not, you know, is you know obviously it says
multiple times in the תורה, Torah ונכרת ונכרת מעמיו Venichrat Venichrat Me'amav
and so on. But it's not so clear, although one might imagine
that the reason for חמץ Chametz is similar to also what we're
about to see, that there's a the one of the only two
מצוות עשה Mitzvot Aseh that you get כרת for the non-performance. All
of these are transgressions. The only two מצוות Mitzvot that you get
כרת for the non-performance and that's חמץ Chametz, and מילה. Milah. So
and not חמץ, Chametz פסח Pesach and מילה. Milah. So it might
be that the חמץ Chametz reason for כרת is linked to the
פסח. Pesach. I'll talk about that when we get to the פסח
Pesach case. But I would say, you know, the normal מאכלות אסורות
Ma'achalot Assurot like נבילה Neveilah or בשר בחלב, Basar BeChalav, I mean,
you know, you go to McDonald's and you have a cheeseburger with
bacon, right? All of the things we most identify with as total
טרייף, Treif, total taboo, those things are לאווין, Lavim, they're not כרת.
And interestingly, you know, archaeologists they know in Israel whether it's a
Jewish settlement or not because no matter how back far back you
go, there will the the places that are Jewish settlements they will
never find pig bones. And even though in all other places throughout
the world, you know, they would pigs would pigs' bones are always
prevalent in these ancient, you know, archaeological digs. But in Israel in
certain locations they're not present at all and that's how they know
that it was a Jewish settlement. It's not the absence of idols
or other things, that they would be.
But pigs! So it's actually quite fascinating how pigs was it's you
know the taboo of pigs even when there are other you know
way way way back.
They were worshipping idols but they weren't eating pigs.
Exactly. ברוך השם. Baruch Hashem. So anyway, okay. So now what?
Temple and the דם Dam and the...
Well that's the thing, דם Dam and כרת are not limited to
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and they're not limited to, you know,
things that could be קרבנות Korbanot actually. חלב Cheilev interestingly is but
דם Dam of a חיה Chaya is also right אסור, Assur, not
just the דם בהמה Dam Behemah and so on. So it's you
know that's just the general sort of constellation of ideas. It's not
exactly limited by that. Okay. והשוחט ומעלה בחוץ, VeHaShochet U'Ma'aleh BaChutz, so
we actually interestingly break off from מאכלות אסורות Ma'achalot Assurot because those
were we're going to get back but those were particularly had a
מקדש Mikdash resonance. So still within the מקדש Mikdash context, if somebody
שוחטs Shochet or brings a קרבן korban. outside of the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, even to God, at the time when you know there's
an איסור במות. Issur Bamot. ואוכל חמץ בפסח. VeOchel Chametz BePesach. So
now back to מאכלות אסורות Ma'achalot Assurot but now without a מקדש
Mikdash resonance. If you eat חמץ chametz on פסח. Pesach. ואוכל ועושה
מלאכה ביום הכיפורים. VeOchel VeOseh Melacha BeYom HaKippurim. And if somebody eats
or does מלאכה Melacha on יום כיפור, right? There it says ונכרת
Venichrat but there's no חיוב מיתה. Chiyuv Mita.
Does that count as one, אוכל ועושה? Ochel VeOseh?
No, two. Either or, those are two. והמפטם את השמן והמפטם את
הקטורת. VeHaMefatem Et HaShemen VeHaMefatem Et HaKetoret. Interesting things that we just
did very recently in the פרשה, Parsha, right? Nothing that probably probably
not too many people have a יצר הרע Yetzer Hara or even
would be have the wherewithal to be able to do this. But
the תורה Torah says in the beginning of is
it כי תשא? Ki Tisa?
It says כי תשא Ki Tisa about making of the שמן המשחה
Shemen HaMishcha and speaks about making of the קטורת, Ketoret, right? And
it says ואתה קח לך בשמים ראש מר דרור VeAtah Kach Lecha
Besamim Rosh Mor Dror etc. etc. ועשית שמן משחת קודש, VeAsita Shemen
Mishchat Kodesh, make for the... the special anointing oil that you're going
to do to anoint all the vessels in the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, משכן, Mishkan, and it says like this, and you וקדשת vekidashta
etcetera, על בשר אדם לא ייסך, al besar adam lo yisach, you
shall not put this oil on the flesh of a human, ובמתכנתו
לא תעשו, u'vematkunto lo sa'asu, so don't take the oil that actually
is the שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishcha and put it on yourself, and
number two, don't make oil comparable with the same ingredients. Don't make
a, don't make your own שמן המשחה. Shemen Hamishcha. ובמתכנתו, u'vematkunto, we're
going to get there, לא תעשו כמהו קדש היא, lo sa'asu kamohu
kodesh hi, איש אשר ירקח כמהו ish asher yirkach kamohu ואשר יתן
ממנו על זר, v'asher yiten mimenu al zar, so if you make
a similar שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishcha or you take the actual שמן
המשחה Shemen Hamishcha and put it on your body, ונכרת מעמיו. venichras
me'amav. And then it says by the קטורת, Ketores, by the incense
that they would burn, similarly it says, והקטרת אשר תעשה במתכנתה לא
תעשו לכם קדש תהיה לך לה'. v'haketores asher ta'aseh b'matkuntah lo sa'asu
lachem kodesh tihyeh lecha la'Hashem. Do not make a, do not make
the קטורת Ketores in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. The one thing
it does not have that's not parallel by the קטורת Ketores is
it does not say that if you smell the actual קטורת Ketores
that you are חייב כרת, chayav kares, but that actually is because
that actually there's not even מעילה me'ilah when you smell the קטורת,
Ketores, smelling is not considered to be biblically be a form of
הנאה. hana'ah. So therefore it is actually not included in this, it's
actually not even a לאו. What if you, what if
you burn the קטורת Ketores outside the מקדש? Mikdash? Oh, that would
be, would that,
that would be a form of like, right, of העלאת חוץ ha'alas
chutz because right, included in שמעלה she'ma'aleh is, right, is, again, I
have to, you're, you're taxing my memory here, but I got to
tell you, before Bar-Ilan, it would not have been a problem. Getting
so lazy in terms of that, but anyway, yes, being מעלה קטורת
בחוץ ma'aleh Ketores bachutz is,
you know what, I'm not going to answer that question. Being מעלה
אברים בחוץ, ma'aleh evarim bachutz, being מקטיר maktir the אברים evarim בחוץ
bachutz or מקטיר חלב בחוץ, maktir cheilev bachutz, that definitely is part
of שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. מעלה קטורת בחוץ, ma'aleh Ketores bachutz, I'm
not so sure that that actually would be considered שחוטי חוץ. shchutei
chutz. שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz is very much around animals.
But smelling is not considered an action, right?
Right. But your question is, is the act of being מעלה בחוץ
ma'aleh bachutz like שחוטי חוץ? shchutei chutz?
Right, but you mentioned that there's no counterpart to סיכת השמן sachas
hashemen
with קטורת Ketores
because there's no action of,
oh, I could go into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and smell
it, right?
And I
could smuggle it out and burn it outside the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, the קטורת Ketores of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
All right,
so that means, so if you make the קטורת, Ketores, so that's,
you know, איסור כרת, issur kares, but am I allowed לכתחילה lechatchila
to buy it from you then and then, you know, put it
in my house?
Right, yes, to the stuff, the קטורת Ketores of the מקדש, Mikdash,
it's only the איסור issur is only on the person who makes
it. I presume, I believe that's correct. והמפטם את השמן, v'hamfatem es
hashemen, so if you make according to the ingredients of the שמן
המשחה, Shemen Hamishcha, והמפטם את הקטרת, v'hamfatem es haketores, or you make
the ingredients of the קטורת, Ketores, this is on your own, in
your own little home laboratory, that you're חייב chayav for making the
exact sort of the, the exact way. Now, I should also say
the perform, exact way, I should also say by the קטורת Ketores
it says, איש אשר, ish asher, by the קטורת Ketores it's you're
allowed to make it in your own home if you're doing it
for the sake of donating it to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
because the פסוק pasuk says, maybe I'm just focused on this because
it was recent and because it's also not so well known, it
says by the קטורת Ketores it says,
לא תעשו לכם, lo sa'asu lachem, and from there we read out
that you cannot do, איש אשר יעשה כמוה להריח בה. ish asher
ya'aseh chamoha le'hariach bah. So the איסור issur making the קטורת Ketores
is only if you want to use it for your own personal
use. But the איסור issur is not smelling it, it's for making
it for your use. You can make the קטורת Ketores to donate
it to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishcha cannot
be made even with the intention to donate.
And you can't smell it.
Yes, okay. So anyway, so okay, so anyway, making the קטורת, Ketores,
making the שמן המשחה, Shemen Hamishcha, although there's slight differences in terms
of what parameters it's forbidden, והסך את שמן המשחה, v'hasach es shemen
hamishcha, or to use the actual שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishcha and to
anoint yourself with it, all those are חייב כרת, chayav kares, and
that's the list of the חיוב כרת chiyuv kares that is transgressions.
Now, there are two that are חייב כרת chayav kares without actually
being negative prohibitions, והפסח והמילה, v'hapesach v'hamila, מצות עשה. mitzvas asei. פסח
Pesach and מילה mila are the only two, are the two that
are מצות עשה mitzvas asei that their non-performance is חייב כרת, chayav
kares, and the Torah is explicit about that, right, by פסח Pesach
it says that איש אשר הוא טהור ובדרך לא היה וחדל לעשות
הפסח ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מעמיה, ish asher hu tahor u'vederech lo hayah
v'chadal la'asos hapesach venichrasah hanefesh hahi me'ameha, right, and by, you know,
and by ברית מילה Bris Mila itself, what's the פסוק pasuk by
ברית מילה? Bris Mila? וערל זכר אשר לא ימול את בשר ערלתו
ונכרתה v'arel zachar asher lo yimol es basar orlaso venichrasah etcetera.
Now why, it's in בראשית Bereishis though.
I understand. Okay, yeah, that's, I'm having things that were said and
not repeated, so apply anyway. What is the reason why these are
חייב כרת? chayav kares? I mean, other than that the Torah says
it. But I would say that these are the two which are,
you know, the primary in terms of Jewish identity. Now, of course,
the מילה mila for men, but the פסח Pesach actually is an
interesting question whether women are obligated or רשות reshus for קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, so acknowledging that what I'm about to say is again
male biased, but within that, these are so sort of foundational. to
that issue of Jewish identity. One is Jewish sort of personal, the
other is communal. One is about sort of the physical mark on
the body, the other is about the foundational story and being part
of that history and part of that community, which is why you
actually see that the people that could not bring the קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, what do they say to משה? Moshe? They say למה
נגרע לבלתי הקריב את קרבן ה' במעדו בתוך בני ישראל? Lama nigara
levilti hikrivas korban Hashem bemoado betoch benei Yisrael? That sense of exclusion
is so profound and that's why you get a makeup for the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach because it is so much about being part
of the nation. Which is why, look, פסח Pesach is coming up
and we can acknowledge the idea of that, it's one of the
rituals that is kept, I don't know what the percentage is, 95%
of people that identify as Jewish do some form of a סדר,
Seder, so it's more
than one of the most universally kept Jewish rituals. There's other reasons
obviously, it's like just a powerful experience the way we've constructed the
סדר, Seder, but it also speaks to this way to which it
is so foundational in terms of that sense of being part of
the Jewish community. So כרת, although we discussed before what כרת means,
פשט הפסוקים, pshat apsukim, כרת is about inclusion in the people. כרת
is also
ונכרת מעמיו, venichrat me'amav, ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מתוך בני ישראל. venichrat hanefesh
hahi mitoch benei Yisrael. Right, I don't even know, you could check
it, I don't even know if כרת appears in the תורה Torah
without the qualifier of מעמיו, me'amav, just ונכרתה הנפש ההיא. Right, the
way we think of כרת, it's a personal punishment, shorter life, no
עולם הבא, whatever, but in the תורה Torah it's very much מעמיו,
me'amav, that somehow that soul is excluded from the people. And that's
clearly why this is, I believe, very clearly why these two are
the מצוות עשה mitzvot asei that there's כרת because that's exactly what
it's about, it's about inclusion or exclusion from the people. Again, acknowledging
the male bias. And that's I think one way of understanding why
חמץ chametz, of all of the מאכלות אסורות ma'achalot asurot is a
חיוב כרת chiyuv Karet as well because that actually is a form
of how
one participates in the חג chag of פסח. Pesach. It's by bringing
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on ערב פסח erev Pesach and by
celebrating חג המצות chag hamatzot for the next seven days. So I
would identify the איסור כרת issur Karet of חמץ, I would connect
it to the כרת that comes with קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Okay,
so these are the things for which you get כרת, some are
מצוות עשה, mitzvot asei, most of them are לא תעשה, lo ta'aseis,
almost, some of them you get a punishment in בית דין beis
din of חייב מיתה, chayav misa, others not, but they're all חייב
כרת chayav Karet when they're done intentionally. And now the משנה Mishnah
goes on,
על אלו חייבין על זדונו כרת, al elu chayavin al zedono Karet,
for these if you willfully transgress, again, you get כרת, assuming there're
no witnesses and warning that could perhaps give you מיתה depending on
the situation, on which sin. ועל שגגתו חטאת, ve'al shigagato chatat, if
however you are negligent and do it unwittingly, unintentionally I should say,
you bring a חטאת. chatas. What does it mean to be unintentional?
Well, one form of unintentional is you had a mistake about the
facts. רש"י Rashi here or Pseudo-רש"י, Rashi, but they quote, describes and
he's basing himself on גמרות, Gemaras, some cases which are almost a
little bit like humorous, like a person thinks that he's having sex
with his wife, a man thinks he's having sex with his wife
and it turns out it was his sister.
So whoops,
okay. But anyway, some types of cases is you make a mistake
with the facts. You didn't realize you were טמא, tamei, you didn't
realize you were entering into the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you didn't
realize it was שבת. Shabbat. The other possibility is that you make
a mistake with the law. Now what type of mistake with the
law? So here the Pseudo-רש"י Rashi basically says that the mistake is
that you know something is אסור assur but you weren't aware that
this specific thing was אסור. assur. Oh, I knew you were not
allowed to do עבודה זרה avoda zara and that you're חייב מיתה,
chayav misa, I just didn't realize that this was considered one of
the acts of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So it's funny, totally realizes
he's in the sort of ambit of doing an act that's חייב
מיתה, chayav misa, but I technically thought that this particular act wasn't
חייב מיתה chayav misa and wasn't actually forbidden. Right, those would be
the types of cases where you did not know that this particular
detail
was actually an act of חייב מיתה chayav misa although you understood
the larger context. What if you didn't know the whole thing was
אסור? assur? Right, if I wouldn't have told you some of this
was, making שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha is אסור, assur, I mean okay
it's מפורש פשוט, meforash pashut, but a lot of people wouldn't know
that. Okay, so would you be considered to be a שוגג shogeg
or not? So that's a category called in the גמרא Gemara. אומר
מותר. omer mutar. Now, is אומר מותר, omer mutar, is it a
שוגג, shogeg, is it worse, is it better? A גמרא Gemara in
מכות Makkot deals with let's say somebody says it's מותר mutar to
kill someone. Are they a שוגג shogeg or not,
in terms of getting going into גלות? galus? And there the גמרא,
Gemara the question is is אומר מותר omer mutar so close to
מזיד, meizid, right, ignorance of law is no excuse, that maybe not
that we would actually give you the punishment of death, but it's
so close to מזיד meizid you're not a שוגג, shogeg, you don't
get גלות. galus. And there that's the question, are you שוגג shogeg
or are you קרוב למזיד? karov lemeizid? And there the גמרא Gemara,
frames it as הוי ליה למידע. havei lei lemeida. Is that something
that we should say, it's your responsibility to know that things are
אסור? assur? Ignorance of the law is no excuse. The Pseudo-רש"י Rashi
here says that אומר מותר omer mutar would be an אונס oness
if you didn't know
something. A lot of that according to ראשונים Rishonim have to do
with case by case do we say הוה ליה למידע hava lei
l'meida or not. So, you know, could be that when it comes
to murder, we say הוה ליה למידע. hava lei l'meida. When it
comes to מפטם
את הקטורת, mefatem es haktoret, even though it's a מפורש פסוק, meforash
pasuk, maybe we would not say הוה ליה למידע. hava lei l'meida.
Wait, what?
According to you, either way it's not שוגג, shogeig, the way you
said it.
No, no, no, it could be straight שוגג, shogeig, it could be
קרוב למזיד, karov l'meizid, it could be almost אונס. oness. It all
depends, it's a spectrum based on an assessment of הוה ליה למידע.
hava lei l'meida. Okay, so that is רש"י Rashi here, pseudo-רש"י Rashi
here says it would be considered אונס, oness, but I'm just putting
out to you that it's not so clear about what the ראשונים
Rishonim all say, I mean whatever, when they discuss it, they basically
say it all depends on the case. Okay, so that's an interesting
question if that constitutes שוגג. shogeig. But some type of mistake of
the facts or of the law makes you a שוגג shogeig and
you bring a חטאת. chatas, What's the difference between
mistake of the law and ignorance of the law?
Well,
no, it is ignorance of the law, but it's ignorance of a
detail rather than of the whole category. Okay, that is the way
that here pseudo-רש"י Rashi explains it. Okay, I don't know if I
should keep saying pseudo-רש"י Rashi the whole time, it sounds a little
funny. But anyway, but what do you call it? But the question
is complete ignorance. Is that considered to be שוגג shogeig or better
or worse? Okay, as opposed to ignorance of a detail. Okay, if
I had no clue that עבודה זרה avodah zarah was אסור, assur,
am I an idiot and that's considered to be not even enough
of a שוגג, shogeig, it's קרוב למזיד? karov l'meizid? Or am I,
oh, completely blameless? Now, קרוב למזיד, karov l'meizid, I should say, is
the fact that it has to be not too much fault is
a concept that we have by רציחה retzichah and by going into
גלות. galus. Normally, by bringing a חטאת, chatas. as long as you're
not intentional, as long as you're שוגג, shogeig, even if it's a
type of a high degree of fault שוגג, shogeig, but as long
as it's not intentional, you would still bring a חטאת. chatas Okay,
so there's a much wider range for bringing a חטאת chatas until
you're real מזיד meizid or until you're real אונס, oness, not just
קרוב למזיד karov l'meizid or קרוב לאונס. karov l'oness. The surprising thing
about this רש"י Rashi is he actually says you're real אונס, oness,
not just קרוב לאונס. karov l'oness. And there so, but so you
would bring a חטאת chatas in those cases. So now if as
long as you weren't actually real מזיד meizid or real אונס. oness.
Now, these are the things you bring a חטאת chatas, for. ולא
הודע שלהם אשם תלוי. V'lo hoda shelahem asham talui. If you might
have done this sin, but you're not sure, again the way sort
of רש"י Rashi describes it is, well, I slept with some woman
last night, I had sex, I don't know if she was my
wife or my sister. Okay, so in that type of a case,
you would bring a אשם תלוי, asham talui, which is a sin
offering for holding something in abeyance, which means that there's a good
grounds to think you sinned, but you're not sure. And we'll discuss
what those grounds are, and in those case you bring an אשם
תלוי. asham talui. חוץ, Chutz, the exception is, מנטמא מקדש וקדשיו. m'nitamei
mikdash v'kodashav. In the one case about somebody who is טמא tamei
and enters in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or eats a קרבן.
korban Those if you do them willfully, you bring a not a
willfully שוגג, shogeig, you know you've done it, you do not bring
a standard חטאת, chatas, you bring an עולה ויורד. oleh v'yored. It
is a חטאת, chatas, but it is of
varying value based on how wealthy or poor you were. And therefore,
מפני שהוא בעולה ויורד, mipnei shehu b'oleh v'yored, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei
Rabbi Meir. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the only thing you
bring an אשם תלוי asham talui for is something that otherwise you
would bring a normal fixed חטאת, chatas, a חטאת קבועה. chatas kavua.
But if something that if you knew you had done it you
would bring a variable cost חטאת, chatas an עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored,
that does not have its counterpart in אשם תלוי. asham talui. Okay,
although yes, it's a חטאת chatas. and it's a כרת and all
these things, but a אשם תלוי asham talui is only something that
otherwise would be a fixed חטאת. chatas? Wait, עולה ויורד? oleh v'yored?
No, you'd bring nothing. עולה ויורד oleh v'yored if you know you
did it, and if you don't know whether you did it, you
know you did it accidentally, and if you don't know whether you
did it accidentally, but you might have, you do nothing. וחכמים אומרים,
V'chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say, אף המגדף. af hamigadeif. Even a
מגדף, migadeif, presumably you do not bring an אשם תלוי asham talui
if a person is uncertain whether they have accidentally, unintentionally blasphemed. שנאמר,
Shene'emar, תורה אחת יהיה לכם לעושה בשגגה, torah achas yihyeh lachem l'oseh
bishgagah, one law for the one who does it in שגגה, shgagah,
in negligence or unintentionally, יצא מגדף שאינו עושה מעשה. yatza migadeif she'eino
oseh ma'aseh.
The blasphemer has not done an action. Now what does that mean?
Are they just excluding him from a אשם תלוי, asham talui, or
are they even excluding him from a חטאת? chatas, It could be
that from a חטאת, chatos right, you require there to be an
action as well. Although interestingly, to put the guy to death or
to give כרת, it could just be verbal, doesn't require a physical
action, but for certain types of קרבנות, korbanot, the חכמים Chachamim are
saying would require an action. So we will see the scope of
that when we get to the גמרא. Gemara Blasphemy is saying the
השם? Hashem? Saying using God's explicit name and cursing God with God's
name. So in the Torah, God should curse God.
Yes, right. And if he doesn't, and there's no instance, it also
says כרת. But question is would he bring a חטאת chatas. if
it were or an אשם תלוי asham talui if it were unintentional
or unintentional and uncertain. Okay, now the גמרא, Gemara let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara. says מניינא למה לי?
minyana lama li? Why do I need to give a number? 36.
Okay, and now it's going to go through a whole list of
things in our מסכת masechet, that give numbers and asks what's the
point of the number? So in the process of doing this I
should say what the גמרא's Gemara going to do is what some
גמרות Gemaras classically do in their opening סוגיא sugya is that they
bring in, they don't really say new things, they bring in a
lot of material later on, they ask more sort of like technical
linguistic questions, and in the process of doing that they introduce you
to, it's like an overview of what you're going to be seeing
in the rest of the מסכת. masechet These סוגיות sugyos are mostly
identified as a סבוראי, Savoraic, already רב שרירא גאון Rav Sherira Gaon
in a classic letter said that there are some סוגיות sugyos like
the ones in the beginning of קידושין Kiddushin that were added later
by the סבוראים, Savoraim, the early גאונים Geonim after the גמרא, and
basically scholars have identified that the ones that are clearly that are
these types that open up a מסכת, masechet. don't really have new
material, and really bring in material from the rest of the מסכת
masechet to give you almost like an opening שיעור shiur to give
you an introduction to the מסכת. masechet. So let's take a look.
מניינא למה לי? minyana lama li? Why do I need this number
36? אמר רב יוחנן, Amar Rav Yochanan, קמשמע לן kamashma lan כולם
בהעלם אחת חייב על כל אחת ואחת. kulam b'helem achas chayav al
kol achas v'achas. This is going to be one of the main
principles that we're going to be talking about in this מסכת masechet.
about how many קרבנות korbonos would you bring if you did a
lot of things in one state of forgetfulness. So if you forgot
all of these 36 prohibitions or relevant details from all of these
36 prohibitions and you did all of them in one state of
being like, you know, like a space cadet, you would bring 36
חטאות. chataos. You don't say that because it was all done in
one big state of forgetfulness that you would only bring one חטאת.
chatas Yes.
There are
34 of them are prohibitions.
Yes, actually that's true. So it'd only be 34. I wasn't counting,
I have to be honest. Was it 36 before you got to
פסח Pesach and מילה Milah or was it 34 before? Were you
counting?
Oh, I wasn't counting. Okay, I just counted actually it's 36 even
with פסח Pesach and מילה.
Milah. All right, we'll have to go back and count.
I don't want to answer you.
Okay, we'll have to go back and count. All right, anyway, but
you're right. Either, but since the גמרא's saying that 36 is to
tell you 36 חטאות. chataos.
I just counted and it is 34 without פסח. Pesach.
Okay, so it's not really 36 חטאות, chataos, it's 34 חטאות. chataos.
Anyway, fine, moving on. ותו הא דתנן, V'su ha d'tenan, that which
we taught in a משנה. Mishna. Now we're going actually to a
different משנה, Mishna, but we'll get back to
our פרק perek in a minute, our מסכת. Masechet. אבות מלאכות ארבעים
חסר אחת. Avos melachos arbaim chaser achas. There are 39 מלאכות melachos
of שבת. Shabbos. מניינא למה לי? minyana lama li? Why do you
have to give a specific number? I mean, just tell me them,
who cares? So, to tell you the principle that you can bring
up to 39 חטאות. chataos. קמשמע לן kamashma lan כולם בהעלם אחת
חייב על כל אחת ואחת. kulam b'helem achas chayav al kol achas
v'achas. If you knew it was שבת Shabbos but forgot that all
these 39 things were אסור, assur, then you would, and you did
all of them, you'd bring 39 חטאות. chataos. We don't just say
it's one form of, it's חילול שבת chilul Shabbos, done multiple times.
It's 39 separate עבירות aveiros and therefore if you did 39 times
of זריעה zriah or 39 בישול, bishul, you'd only bring one חטאת
chatas in one state of forgetfulness. Right? That's the point here, that
if it's one state of forgetfulness and the same sin, you only
bring one חטאת chatas. no matter how many times you did it.
But since it's 39 distinct מלאכות, melachos, you bring 39 sins. The
גמרא in שבת Shabbos wants to know then how did you remember
it was שבת Shabbos if you thought all those things were מותר?
muttar? So it says, okay, well you still knew for example that
it was אסור assur to go חוץ לתחום chutz l'tchum or something.
Okay, anyway, but okay, that's not our topic right now. To say
the same point though, that even if it's all about חילול שבת,
you can bring 39 חטאות. chataos. Okay, ותו הא דתנן. V'su ha
d'tenan. Now we're going, so that's about multiple חטאות. chataos. Now we're
going to go later in our מסכת. maseches, We teach later the
beginning of the next פרק, perek, ארבעה מחוסרי כפרה. arba'ah mechusrei kaparah.
There are four types of sin offerings which are about the completing
of the purification process. They really are not about sin, but are
about somebody that was טמא tamei that the תורה says that this
is what you need to become fully טהור tahor and to be
able to enter into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and eat קרבנות,
korbonos, you have to end the process by bringing a חטאת. Chatat,
So מניינא למה לי? minyana lama li? Why does it say exactly
four? What's that coming to teach me? It's not, so לאפוקי, l'apokei,
that's not about sinning and about bringing multiple, it's about a purification
process. So לאפוקי מדרבי אליעזר בן יעקב, l'apokei mi'd'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov,
to tell you that it's rejecting the position of רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, דאמר חמשה הוי, d'amar chamisha havei, that
he says that there are actually five. So the משנה Mishna emphasizes
there are only four, it should be clear that it rejects רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. דתניא, D'tanya, or it should
be דתנן, d'tenan, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר גר מחוסר כפרה עד
שיזרק דם עליו. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer ger mechusar kaparah ad
she'yizarek dam alav. So it's actually a גר ger has to, a
convert has to bring a קרבן korban to complete the process of
conversion. It's actually interesting, so the גמרא asks, so how do we
do conversion nowadays? We'll see that when we get to the גמרא.
But according to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, the
קרבן korban is not about completing the process of conversion, the קרבן
Korban is about allowing him to eat קרבנות korbonos and it is
a status, it's like a normal מחוסר כפרה, mechusar kaparah, it's about
a purification type.
But since you say four, you should just listen for.
I understand, but we're emphasizing so there should be no confusion, it
should be very clear that we're rejecting it. Okay, so הכי קתני.
hachi katani. So הכי תנא ארבע. Hachi tanna arba. So therefore it
said four to show you only four and not his position. ותו
הא דתנן, Ve-tu ha detnan, that which we taught in the משנה,
Mishnah, ארבע מביאין על הזדון כשגגה. Arba mevi'in al ha-zadon ki-shogegah. Again,
this we'll also be getting this in our מסכת. There are some
types of people that bring קרבנות Korbanot even if they are willful
sinners, right? You have cases of עולה ויורד, Oleh ve-Yored, not a
classic חטאת, Chatat but you do have certain types of קרבנות Korbanot
for sin even if it's for a willful sinner. Those more are
the sort of non-חטאת Chatat things, standard חטאת chatas like עולה ויורד
Oleh ve-Yored or אשם, Asham, not all of them, but some of
them are even for in case of a willful sin. So why
does it say four? You see how you're getting a nice overview
of the topics we're going to be discussing. Okay, why does it
say four? מניינא למה לי? Minyana lama li? Why does it need
four? לאפוקי מדרבי שמעון Le-apukei mi-de-Rabbi Shimon to show you to exclude
the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon explicit clearly. דתניא De-tanya we
taught in a ברייתא Braita רבי שמעון אומר שבועת הפקדון לא ניתן
זדונה לכפרה. Rabbi Shimon omer shevuat ha-pikadon lo nitan zedonah le-kapparah. No,
if you take a false oath about a, about a not having
a, an object for safekeeping, a פקדון pikadon in your house, somebody
gave you something to watch and you deny it and you take
a false oath, that you would only bring a קרבן Korban. if
it was שוגג, shogeg, if you were willful you do not have
the atonement of a קרבן. Korban So he actually says there are
not four there are three. So we said no four to show
you that we don't agree with him. So one case was four
but not five, here it's four but not three. Okay, הכי תני
ארבע. Hachi tani arba. Therefore we say four. ותו הא דתנן Ve-tu
ha detnan how about that which we taught in the משנה Mishnah
חמשה מביאים קרבן אחד על עבירות הרבה? Chamishah mevi'im Korban echad al
aveirot harbeh? It's sort of another type of, of exception to the
general rule. There are five types of people that can bring one
קרבן Korban for multiple transgressions. Normally you need a separate קרבן Korban
for each transgression. So מניינא למה לי? Minyana lama li? Why do
I need a number to tell me five? What's that excluding? משום
דקבעי למיתני סיפא נזיר שנטמא טומאות הרבה Mishum de-ka-ba'ei le-mitni seifa nazir
she-nitma tumot harbeh because one of the examples, it's not really about
an עבירה, aveirah, is about a נזיר. Nazir. I mean it's sort
of, a נזיר Nazir can't become טמא, tamei, but the קרבן Korban
is more about a process of beginning the נזירות nezirot again. Anyway,
it has an example of a, of a נזיר Nazir bringing multiple
קרבנות. Korbanot. Now what is the example? So the example is the
following: he became טמא tamei multiple times. ומשכחת לה כגון דנטמא בשביעי
וחזר ונטמא בשביעי. U-mashkachat lah kegon de-nitma be-shvi'i ve-chazar ve-nitma be-shvi'i. That
basically the idea is like this: if a נזיר Nazir
when he has to become טהור, tahor, it's a seven-day purification process
and then he starts his נזירות nezirot again. Which day does he
start his נזירות טהרה? nezirot taharah? We're going to see that there's
a debate. Does he start his נזירות טהרה nezirot taharah on day
seven when the purification is over, or does he start it on
day eight when he brings the קרבן Korban? that he brings to
sort of end the, you know, and to start to restart to
end the purification, you know, through the bringing of a קרבן? Korban
So there's a debate whether it's day seven or a day eight.
But the קרבן Korban, is only brought for the טומאה tumah on
day eight. So here's the, here's the idea. If you start the
process again at day seven, then what happens if you were day
seven, you were, you became טמא, tamei, day seven you became טהור,
tahor, okay, and now you became טמא tamei again, okay, and then
right there on that same day. And then you did it again
and then the same day seven you, you started your process again
and on that day you became טמא tamei again. So that type
of a case you have multiple טומאות tumot because of distinct נזירויות
nezirot because you started them again. But because it occurred to you
prior to day eight, prior to any time when you were obligated
in a קרבן, Korban you are only going to bring one קרבן
Korban, on those multiple events. If you had become טמא tamei on
day eight after, after you had become obligated in a קרבן, Korban
then you would bring two, one קרבן Korban for that and one
קרבן Korban, for the next. But because your טומאה tumah occurred before
you were obligated in a קרבן, Korban then there is only one
קרבן Korban for these multiple events. Okay, so that is similar to
one קרבן Korban on עבירות הרבה. aveirot harbeh. It's not exactly עבירות
הרבה, aveirot harbeh, it's not so much about the sin, but anyway
it is one קרבן Korban. for these multiple things. Okay,
so therefore ומשכחת לה כגון דנטמא בשביעי וחזר ונטמא בשביעי. u-mashkachat lah
kegon de-nitma be-shvi'i ve-chazar ve-nitma be-shvi'i. ומני רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה היא.
U-mani Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehudah hi. It's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yose be-Rabbi Yehudah. דאמר נזירות דטהרה משביעי הוא דחיילא עליה. De-amar nezirot
de-taharah mi-shvi'i hu de-chaila aleih. That he says that you start your
new נזירות nezirot on day seven although you're not yet obligated in
a קרבן. Korban So you started your new נזירות nezirot on day
seven, then you became טמא tamei on that selfsame day. So therefore
when day eight hits you're not, you're not in a position to
bring a קרבן Korban. yet, you're already, you're still טמא tamei again.
Okay, so in that type of a case you had multiple distinct
טומאות tumot because your new נזירות nezirot started, but you don't have
multiple קרבנות Korbanot because you were not yet obligated in a קרבן.
Korban דאי תימא רבי היא, De-i teima Rabbi hi, if you were
to say it's רבי Rabbi who says you only start counting the
new נזירות nezirot on day eight, כיון דנזירות דטהרה עד שמיני לא
חיילא עליה, keivan de-nezirot de-taharah ad shmini lo chaila aleih, since the
new נזירות nezirot does not begin until day eight, היכי משכחת לה?
heichi mashkachat lah? You'll never have a case of one קרבן korban
for multiple טומאות. tumot. אי דנטמא בז' וחזר ונטמא בז', Ei de-nitma
be-zayin ve-chazar ve-nitma be-zayin, if the טומאה tumah came on day seven,
כולה חדא טומאה אריכתא היא. kulah chada tumah arichta hi. According to
him it's not a, it's not for multiple status, statuses of נזירות,
nezirot, right? Because your new status of נזירות, nezirot, your new נזירות
nezirot only began on day eight. So your נזירות nezirot didn't begin,
so it's all one טומאה tumah נזירות, nezirot, it's not multiple נזירות.
nezirot. נזירות neziruses that became טמא. tamei. ואי איתמי בשמיני, ve-i-itme bashmini,
and if you became טמא tamei on day eight when you began
your new נזירות, nezirus, וחזר ואיתמי בשמיני, ve-chazar ve-itme bashmini, כיון דיצא
בשעה הראויה להביא בקרבן, keivan de-yatza b'shas haruya l'havi b'korban, since when
day eight began, you were obligated in a קרבן korban. for your
past טומאה, tumah, now you became טמא tamei again, you know, that's
a new קרבן. korban, Your other קרבן, korban, your obligation already existed.
חייב על כל אחת ואחת, chayav al kol achas v'achas,
you have to bring separate קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so is this concept
here clear? It's basically if you can start a new נזירות nezirus
and have a new טומאה tumah and still not yet be obligated
in a קרבן, korban, then when you finally get obligated in a
קרבן, korban it can count for all the different events. But if
you can only start your new one on day eight after you've
been obligated, then it's separate קרבנות. korbanot. אלא שמע מינה רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה היא. ella shma mina Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda hi.
So you see it's רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda.
So the reason to say basically to emphasize five is רש"י Rashi
says so you shouldn't be confused and think maybe נזירות nezirus isn't
included and maybe it was רבי. Rebbe. We tell you five so
you know that we're including the position of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda who says this concept, this idea of נזירות.
nezirus. Now, מאי רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה? mai Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda?
Just quickly to fill in those blanks, what are we referring to?
דתניא: de-tanya: וקדש את ראשו ביום ההוא. v'kiddash es rosho bayom hahu.
He will sanctify his head on that day, the נזיר nazir that
was טמא, tamei, meaning he'll begin his נזירות nezirus again on
that day. Which day? מאי ביום ההוא? mai bayom hahu? ביום הבאת
קרבנותיו, bayom ha-vas korbanosav, דברי רבי. divrei Rebbe. On the day you
bring your קרבן korban on day eight, that's when you start your
new נזירות nezirus after you've already been obligated in a קרבן korban
for the old stuff. רבי, Rebbe, that's what רבי Rebbe says. רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda omer: no, ביום תגלחתו.
bayom tiglachto. On the day that he does his shaving of his
head, so even before he's obligated in a קרבן korban. on day
seven, he is able to begin his new נזירות. nezirus. And that's
how you can have multiple נזירות neziruses without ever having been yet
obligated in a קרבן. korban, Okay, so that is... so what do
we have? We have cases of bringing קרבנות korbanot for... the idea
of multiple קרבנות korbanot for, you know, for one state of forgetfulness.
We have the idea of bringing קרבנות korbanot not based on sin
but based on atonement, on כפרה. kapparah. We have bringing some types
of sin offerings are brought for willful, even willful sins. Some types,
sometimes you'll bring a sin offering for multiple sins or for multiple
events and not just one per, which has been the rule until
now. Okay, so so far that's a nice overview of topics and
משניות mishnayos we'll be seeing. And here's another one: הא דתנן, had-t'nan,
הם מביאים קרבן עולה ויורד. hem mevi'im korban oleh v'yored. That's another
special category of קרבנות, korbanot, right, which we mentioned in the first
משנה. mishna. A sin offering that is a variable cost based on
your ability to pay for it. And there are five of those,
five עולה ויורד. oleh v'yored. מניינא למאי? minyana l'mai? Why mention five?
משום דתני סיפא: mishum d'tani seifa: נשיא כיוצא בהם. nasi k'yotzei bahem.
Because we say at the end that a נשיא nasi is like
them. It's really not so much the סיפא, seifa, but anyway, we
say in הוריות, Horayos, what... who is like who? The גמרא says
that when a בית דין beis din rules incorrectly and כלל ישראל
Klal Yisrael listens and sins or whatever, you know, that's a case
where the בית דין beis din could bring פר העלם דבר של
ציבור, par helam davar shel tzibbur, the sin offering for this communal
sin that they caused. Now, a נשיא nasi also brings a special
קרבן, korban, a goat, a male goat when a נשיא nasi sins,
which is a prince, a king, whoever it is. Anyway, what types
of sins does a נשיא nasi bring his special קרבן korban חטאת?
chatas, So the משנה mishna says only the types of sins that
the בית דין beis din would bring their special חטאת chatas, for.
Now what is that? Those are sins that when a Jew, a
normal layperson does them, you bring a fixed חטאת, chattas a חטאת
קבועה. chatas kavua. But if a normal person did them would bring
an עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored, this variable cost חטאת, then the בית
דין beis din would not bring a sin if they פסק paskened
and everybody and misled the people. Similarly, the משנה mishna says: נשיא
כיוצא בהם. nasi k'yotzei bahem. If a נשיא nasi sins on a
sin of עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored, he doesn't bring any sin offering.
He doesn't bring a חטאת because it's an עולה ויורד oleh v'yored
sin, and he doesn't bring an עולה ויורד oleh v'yored because he's
not in a category of ever being of variable cost, right? He's...
by virtue of being a נשיא, nasi, he has to be rich.
So he doesn't bring anything. Okay, נשיא כיוצא בהם. nasi k'yotzei bahem.
Either he doesn't bring anything or...
there is an opinion
that he does bring an עולה ויורד. oleh v'yored.
According to the opinion he
doesn't bring
anything, how does he get כפרה? kapparah? He just doesn't. It's tough
life, it's a tough job being a נשיא. nasi. Okay, anyway, so
that's what the משנה mishna says there, that a נשיא nasi would
not bring... would not bring
his special קרבן, korban.
and... maybe not even any קרבן korban. for an עולה ויורד. oleh
v'yored. So therefore, and therefore לאתויי מרבי אליעזר, l'atuyei mi-Rabbi Eliezer, to
exclude רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דאמר נשיא מביא שעיר, d'amar nasi meivi
sa'ir, that a נשיא nasi does bring his special קרבן. So how
is the... his שעיר, sa'ir, his male goat, even by an עולה
ויורד oleh v'yored sin? So by saying that there are five that
are עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored, we are basically saying that... that you
know, that these sins are only... the only thing you will bring
for them is an עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored, you will not bring...
a נשיא nasi will not bring his special קרבן. Okay, ותו, v'su,
הא דתנן, had-t'nan, that which we taught in the משנה. mishna. Now
we're done with our overview of the מסכת, and now we get
to just wrapping up other times where there are numbers. That which
we taught in the משנה: mishna: ארבעה אבות נזיקין. arba avos nezikin.
At the beginning of בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*, there are four categories
of damage, of damage to property, שור, בור *Shor, Bor*, etc. מנא
לן *Minanalan*? Why mention four? לאפוקי מדרבי אושעיא *Lafukei mid'Rabbi Oshaya*, to
reject the idea of רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya*, דאמר תלת עשרי אבות
נזיקין *d'amar telat esrei avot nezikin*, he counts 13. Now obviously to
count 13, he goes beyond the normal list of like when you
or your property damage. He counts other types of things as well,
and the גמרא *Gemara* in בבא קמא *Bava Kamma* discusses what's the
point of having this list. One of the points is that if
you do it and you pay for your damages through land, you
have to pay with מיטב שדהו *meitav sadeihu*, the best of your
land. Anyway, he creates a list of 13, so we're saying that's
not our list. ולרבי אושעיא מנינא דלמה לי *U'l'Rabbi Oshaya minyana d'lamah
li*? According to רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya*, why say 13? So you
could have said just 13 is to reject four, right? Any number
is to reject another number. But the גמרא *Gemara* assumes that it's
rejecting a higher number. לאפוקי מדרבי חייא *Lafukei mid'Rabbi Chiyya*, to reject
רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiyya*, דאמר עשרין וארבעה אבות נזיקין *d'amar esrin v'arba'ah
avot nezikin*, there are 24. ולרבי חייא מנינא דלמה לי *U'l'Rabbi Chiyya
minyana d'lamah li*? Why does he say 24? Again, you could say
to reject 13, but no, no more than 24. So there are
some that are not included in the list even according to his
very expansive list. What's not included? לאפוקי מוסר ומפגל *Lafukei moser u'mefagel*,
when you actually tell on, you know, sort of report somebody to
the government and as a result, מוסר *moser* essentially, as a result
they seize the person's property. This was
obviously in a context in which the government was oppressive and not
seen as a legitimate government. Or you cause פיגול *pigul*, let's say
a כהן *Kohen* and you have a פיגול *pigul* thought to their
קרבן *korban*, so you cause the person a loss, but you did
not directly do it, you only caused it, and it was היזק
שאינו ניכר *hezek she'eino nikar*. It's not a physical type of a
damage that you've done, and therefore those cases you are exempt. That's
the principle of היזק שאינו ניכר *hezek she'eino nikar*. So that's what
he is excluding. Okay. So that goes through all of the numbers.
Let's just, it's already 8:30. Do we have what time is it?
Is it exactly 8:30? All right, so we will have to pick
up with this. All right, so we'll pick up with this. At
least we finished the numbers. We'll pick up with this.